One day, as Hiroki Okamoto was walking to a restaurant with his classmates,
有一天，岡本弘毅和同學前往餐廳時
he noticed that the town was overflowing with advertisements.
發現城市裡到處都刊登著廣告
Ads were in every corner of the restaurant,
不只是餐廳內的各個角落
and even in the restrooms.
甚至連廁所裡面也有
Soon, Okamoto realized that it was hard to distinguish
岡本漸漸開始分辨不出什麼是廣告
between what was an ad and what wasn't.
什麼不是廣告
He wondered if the things he thought he had discovered had actually been ads.
即使是自己找到的 也會想說其實可能都是廣告
For example, this restaurant.
像是這間餐廳
Had he been lured into selecting a restaurant
自己是不是也在無形中被誘導
that appeared at the top of a website?
而選了網頁上方的店？
That was delicious. Thanks for bringing us here.
這裡的菜很好吃耶 謝謝你帶我們來這家店
What is that?
那是什麼？
They found out through social media that that was a giant orifice.
三人透過社群網路得知那是巨大的洞
Do you think it's been there while we were eating?
在我們吃飯時就有這個洞？
Let's go take a closer look.
我們靠近點去看看吧
Unbelievable.
難以置信
-Oh my. -What's going on?
-天啊 -發生了什麼事？
What on earth is that?
這到底是怎麼回事？
-Wow. -It's huge.
-哇 -好大啊
-What is that? -It's floating.
-這是什麼？ -浮在空中耶
-Unbelievable. It's so close… -Whoa.
-不可思議 -超大的
I…
我…
I still remember a dream I had when I was in elementary school.
還記得小學時做過的夢
It's about me and my family going to visit my grandmother during summer break.
在夢中小學生的我和家人一起 在暑假回老家看奶奶
She lived in Sendai.
她雖然住在仙台
From there, we had to change trains three times,
但是必須從那裡換三次電車
then ride the bus for 40 minutes and walk for 15 minutes from there.
坐40分鐘的公車 然後再走15分鐘才會到
That's why we usually went to my grandmother's by car.
所以我們平時去奶奶家時都是開車去
But in my dream, we were going by train for some reason.
但不知道為什麼 我們在夢中是坐電車去的
As an elementary school kid, I hadn't realized it was a dream at the time,
小學生的我 在那時候還沒有察覺這是夢
so I was traveling by train without any doubt.
所以毫不遲疑地坐著電車
Then transferred onto the bus.
然後轉乘公車
BUS STOP
（公車站）
One side of the road faced the sea, where the morning sun shone.
筆直的道路有一邊面海 閃耀著早晨的陽光
On the other side were mountains and the evening sun.
另一邊則有夕陽照射著
You must be hot.
外頭很熱吧
Not really.
不會啊
Since February,
從2月開始
I haven't been able to change the light bulb in the bathroom.
我就換不了廁所的燈泡
It's been out since your grandfather passed away.
從老爺子死了之後就放著不管到現在
There are so many things I can't handle on my own.
有很多這種靠我一個人應付不了的事
I also can't reach high places when I'm cleaning.
一個人打掃也有清不到的地方
I'll do it.
我幫你
Do you want me to ask your neighbors for help?
我們去拜託鄰居來幫忙，好嗎？
Don't bother.
我怎樣都無所謂啦
Can I have ice cream?
我可以吃冰嗎？
This is good meat, you know?
肉質很好
Yasuo's son brought it.
是靖男先生的兒子拿過來給我的
I don't have a driver's license, so it's tough for me
我沒有駕照，買東西很辛苦
but he has one.
但他有汽車駕照
You can have ice cream later.
把冰淇淋留到飯後吃比較好吧
Okay.
對
You know…
我啊…
I can't do anything on my own anymore.
憑一己之力什麼都辦不到
The sun will be shining and the temperatures are expected to rise.
預估在強烈陽光照射下易形成高溫
Along the Pacific coast, temperatures are expected to exceed 30 degrees Celsius,
以西日本至東日本 靠太平洋側地區為中心
resulting in higher temperatures than usual for this time of the year.
預測氣溫將超過30度，高於往年平均
We're getting up at 5 a.m. tomorrow.
明天早上五點要起床
Yes, I'm going to bed.
所以我要睡了
Good night, Grandma.
晚安，奶奶
Good night.
晚安
Dangerously high temperatures are forecasted in many areas…
大範圍地區將是危險的高溫 請注意中暑…
So, I checked the time.
然後我看了一下時鐘
It was 9:30 p.m.
已經是晚上的9點30分了
I had already taken a bath after all.
我應該洗過澡了
But I couldn't remember how I'd done it, and that's when I realized I was dreaming.
在我心想自己是怎麼洗澡時 就發覺這是一場夢
That's why…
所以…
I tried to recall what had happened before this dream.
我試著想起自己入夢前發生的事
Before I went to bed…
就是睡前發生了什麼
I was definitely at home.
我很確定自己在老家
I had gone to school and had played with my friends.
去學校上學，和朋友出去玩
I had eaten dinner, taken a bath,
吃完晚餐，去洗澡
and gotten into my own bed.
最後在自己的床上睡覺
But…
然而…
even though I was dreaming, I started feeling sleepy.
明明在夢中，我卻越來越想睡
I thought if I went to sleep and woke up,
我想說如果睡著後起來
maybe this dream would be over too.
也許就能從夢中醒過來
You're up early.
起得真早啊
Yeah…
是啊
Are you ready to go?
準備好出門了嗎？
Not yet.
還沒
Dad.
爸爸
Have you ever gone to sleep in a dream?
你有在夢中睡著過嗎？
Hm?
嗯？
When you go to sleep and wake up in your dream,
在夢中睡著，然後醒來之後
you have to wake up one more time to return to the real world.
還要再醒一次才能回到真正的世界吧
Yeah, that makes sense.
照理說是該那樣啦
If this were a dream, what would you do, Dad?
如果這只是一場夢，爸爸會怎麼做？
I guess I'd want to design my dream however I wanted to.
那我想試著自由地創造自己的夢境
I think…
我覺得…
this is a dream.
這是一場夢
Oh?
哦？
Then try doing whatever you want.
那你就自由地嘗試吧
You'll catch fish in no time.
立刻就能釣到魚
Just make yourself believe.
要相信你能釣得到
I'm serious.
不是在開玩笑
This is a dream.
這真的是夢
Yeah, so believe you can catch fish.
是啊，所以要相信自己釣得到魚
Come on, believe it.
來，試著這麼想
Look over there.
看著那裡
And imagine it. Imagine yourself catching fish.
然後想像，想像釣到魚的樣子
That the fish is pulling the line.
想像魚拉扯著魚線
Oh.
哦
Wow.
哇
Follow me.
去那邊吧
Okay.
好
What's wrong?
你沒事吧？
It's your grandfather.
你爺爺啊
He said he wanted to live longer.
他說過想要再活久一點
When I thought about why we had to age,
一想到為什麼我們得變老
I couldn't stop crying.
眼淚就掉了下來
The next thing I realized…
接著等我回神
was that I was back in bed again.
我又在被窩裡
I thought I was at home.
還以為是在自己家裡
But from the morning sun I could see in the window,
但從眼前的窗戶所看到的晨光
I immediately realized I was at my grandmother's.
讓我馬上就知道這裡是奶奶的家
Because there is no sea near my grandmother's house.
因為她家附近沒有海
As I thought to myself I was still dreaming…
當我認為自己還在做夢…
I felt a presence behind me.
我感覺到背後好像有人
My grandmother was watching me.
奶奶正看著我
I checked with half-open eyes so she wouldn't notice.
為了不被發現，我瞇著眼睛確認
She was whispering something the whole time.
奶奶她一直在小聲地嘟囔
Her voice was softer than the sound of the clock ticking.
用著比時鐘的滴答聲 還小的聲音說著話
I want to switch places.
真想交換
Please let me switch.
拜託換成我
Let me switch places.
換成我吧
At first, I didn't understand who she wanted to switch places with.
我一開始沒有意會到她想跟什麼調換
But I was scared.
但覺得很害怕
So I wanted to go to sleep and shut my eyes tightly.
所以我用力閉上眼，希望能趕快睡著
But…
但是…
Since I was scared, it was getting harder to sleep.
心裡的恐懼讓我越來越難入睡
Then I realized something.
可是在心裡想著
Since this was a dream,
因為這是一場夢
I actually had to wake up.
我必須醒過來才行
Because this was a dream,
這就是一場夢
so…
所以…
I pinched my thigh several times under the covers.
我在被窩中捏了自己的大腿好幾下
Dad?
爸爸？
Mom?
媽媽？
What's wrong?
怎麼了？
Where are…
爸爸他們…
Dad and Mom?
在哪裡？
I don't know.
不知道
Anyway, do you want some of this?
別管他們了，你想喝點這個嗎？
No, thanks. I'm not thirsty.
不用，我現在不渴
It's good for your health.
但是這有益健康啊
No, thanks. Did Dad and Mom say anything?
不用了，爸爸他們沒有說什麼嗎？
It's good for you.
這對身體很好喔
No, I'm good.
不，我不喝
You're not hungry?
你不餓嗎？
You want me to make breakfast?
要我做早餐嗎？
I don't need breakfast. Where are Dad and Mom?
不要管早餐了，爸爸他們到底在哪？
We're back.
我們回來了
Where have you been?
你們去哪了？
Your grandmother wanted us to go to the Otas'
你奶奶說之前跟太田家借了東西
because she had borrowed something from them.
要我們去一趟，所以我們照做了
What's wrong?
你怎麼了？
You want to eat breakfast?
是想吃早餐吧？
Crying like that will turn you into Grandma.
突然開始哭會變成奶奶喔
Just kidding.
開玩笑的
I was seriously fed up.
我覺得已經受夠了
Why are you gargling?
你為什麼要漱口呢？
My grandmother had that bottle in her hands.
奶奶的手裡拿著瓶子
She started begging me to drink that drink again and…
當她又開始拜託我喝下去的時候…
Stop it!
住手！
In moments like this…
像這種時候
In movies, they startle the person to wake them up, right?
如果是電影的話 會靠著給予刺激讓人驚醒吧？
But all pinching my thigh did was hurt me.
但就算捏大腿，我也只是覺得痛
Today's a short school day, so double check what you need.
今天學校上課時間比較短 確認一下要帶什麼去
I woke up at home,
我在家裡醒來
and it was three days before summer break.
時間是暑假開始的三天前
Morning.
早啊
Are we going to Grandma's again this year?
今年也要去奶奶家嗎？
Why do you ask?
為什麼這麼問？
I don't feel like going this year.
我今年不是很想去
We're not going this year.
今年不去喔
Or ever.
準確來說
When your Grandpa died, we sold that house.
你爺爺也死了，那房子早就賣掉了
Coming to think of it, my grandmother had passed away last year.
仔細想想，奶奶其實在去年就過世了
She had actually passed away before my grandfather.
她比爺爺還要早過世
So then…
所以呢…
I realized that
說起來
I had already been dreaming when I assumed we were going to my grandmother's.
從我以為要去奶奶家的那一刻起 就是在做夢
And…
然後啊
I couldn't remember when I had started assuming that.
我開始困惑那到底是什麼時候
When I try to recall when I had this dream,
當我回想這到底是什麼時候做的夢
it feels like it was when I was in elementary school.
感覺像是讀小學的時候
But it also feels like it could've been later on.
但也有可能是在很久以後做的夢
I mean, today I'm fine and I have a regular job.
雖然我現在有好好地在工作
But ever since that dream,
但有點像是後續
I've been living with a feeling of constant mental fog.
這輩子一直都活得很恍惚
It's not like I have trouble in everyday life.
不過對日常生活沒有造成影響
It just…
就覺得…
gets me thinking that I'll keep getting older like this.
我會以這種狀態不斷老去
And…
然後…
I'm still not sure
我果然還是在猶豫
if I really should enter the orifices.
不曉得要不要進去洞裡
I think that's okay.
那樣也沒什麼不好的啊
After all, Mr. Ozawa did say we could choose for ourselves.
小澤先生也說不管進不進去都可以
-Here you go. -Thanks.
-這給你 -謝謝
How many more days are you all staying here?
大家還要在這住幾天？
I haven't decided yet.
我還沒決定
What time is it now?
現在幾點了？
It's ten o'clock.
十點
Wow, it's pretty late already.
哇，比想像中的還要晚啊
Should we clean up tomorrow?
明天再收拾如何？
Hm…
嗯…
Let's do it today.
今天就收一收吧
-Let's do it. -Okay.
-來收吧 -好
Okay, then.
整理一下吧
Oh, let me.
哦，讓我來
-I'll take the dishes. -Thanks.
-我來拿碗 -謝謝
I'll put away the chairs.
我幫你
The first thing you need to understand is
首先你需要理解的是
that people can only share fiction.
人與人能共有的只有虛構之物
What do you mean?
這是什麼意思？
You might perceive something as red.
也就是說沒有辦法證明
But you can't prove that someone else is seeing the same shade of red, right?
你覺得是紅色的東西 在別人眼裡也是同樣的紅色，對吧？
Look at this, for example.
舉例來說，你看這個
This is blue, right?
這是藍色吧？
Yes.
是藍色的
But you can't know if we are perceiving it as the exact same shade of blue.
但無法確定我們認知的藍色有多藍 或是不是同一種藍
Can you?
誰都不會知道吧？
Right.
的確如此
We can only communicate things through verbal symbols.
人們共有的僅有言語的記號
The same goes for the orifices.
洞也是同樣的道理
You're not entering the orifices, Mr. Ozawa?
小澤先生，你不進去嗎？
Okamoto was pondering.
岡本沉思著
Does living a long life really equal happiness?
長命百歲真的是幸福的嗎？
That is what he was asking himself.
他如此問著自己
At the same time, he thought about aging.
岡本同時也在思考關於老去這件事
He also wondered if the part of his life he had recorded
然後他開始懷疑 自己所記錄下來的部分人生
should be told as his own life story.
是否能作為自己的人生故事 講述給別人聽
It started to snow.
下雪了
But Okamoto did not move.
但岡本沒有動
He was so deeply absorbed in his thoughts that even the snow didn't bother him.
因為他思索時極具專注力 連雪都不在意
However, the next thing Okamoto thought of was
可是岡本下一個想到的事情
that there was a café nearby that he liked.
是在這附近有一間自己喜歡的咖啡廳
A few seconds after the thought of hot coffee crossed his mind,
在熱咖啡掠過腦海的數秒後
he realized that it was snowing.
岡本注意到現在正在下雪
At his favorite café,
在他中意的那間咖啡廳裡
there was a cat.
有一隻貓
It's a small shop.
那是一間小咖啡廳
They renovated a laundromat that was next to a public bathhouse.
是從大眾澡堂旁併設的 洗衣店所改造的
That's why,
所以說啊
there still is one small washer in the café.
店裡還留著一台小型的滾筒洗衣機
Then I suddenly realized that it was the end of the year.
但我意識到如今已經是年底了
Subtitle translation by: Mariko Yasuoka-Sator
字幕翻譯：黃可涵